Finding Aid for the C. George Mayfield Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
George Mayfield Papers
1981-1998
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0288
.834 linear feet
Biographical Sketch
Dr. George R. Mayfield, M.A. 1904, Ph.D. 1915 was born March 21, 1877 and died December 17,1964. Dr. Mayfield was a member of the Vanderbilt faculty from 1904 until his retirement in 1947. He was a professor and Chairman of the German Department. He was also chairman of the faculty lecture series and secretary of Phi Beta Kappa. He taught at the George Peabody College Summer School from 1914 to 1930. He was Treasurer of the College Inn Corporation, which attempted to create a College Inn building adjacent to the Vanderbilt campus in 1920. He was president of the Modern Language section of the Tennessee Teachers’ Association. Dr. Mayfield was instrumental in founding the Tennessee Academy of Science, the Tennessee Conservation League, the Tennessee Historical Association, the Tennessee Ornithological Society, the Nashville Children’s Museum, and the Nashville Lions Club. He was also the editor of the Journal of the Tennessee Academy of Science. George Mayfield also served as a columnist for the Nashville Banner newspaper and wrote the “Fins, Furs, and Feathers” column from 1948 to 1958.
Scope and Content Note
The George Mayfield Papers, 1900-1966, contain correspondence, music, theatre, language, and science programs, newspaper clippings, a calendar, and personal writings that touch on the many associations and organizations in which Dr. Mayfield held membership or interest.
- George Mayfield Correspondence
  - to Dr. George R. Mayfield from Nat T. Winston, June 12, 1950 (Box 1, File 1)
  - to Dr. George R. Mayfield from Edwin T. Nance, February 6, 1955 (Box 1, File 1)
- College Inn Correspondence
  - Correspondence from Arch Trawick to A.M. Souby, August 26, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to Arch Trawick from A.M. Souby, August 27, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to George Mayfield, May 5, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Copy Correspondence to E.B. Craig from William Swiggart, September 15, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to A.M. Souby from William Swiggart, September 18, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to E.B. Craig from A.M. Souby, September 25, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to William Swiggart A.M. Souby, September 27, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to A.M. Souby from A.L. Sharber, October 29, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to A.M. Souby from Harry Frahn, November 17, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to Harry Frahn from A.M. Souby, December 10, 1920 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to A. Max Souby from Thomas Luck, April 27, 1921 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to Thomas Luck from A.M. Souby, May 3, 1921 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to Thomas Luck, May 23, 1921 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Correspondence to Thomas Luck from A.M. Souby, June 22, 1921 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Check to Arch Trawick, April 15, 1918 (Box 1, File 2)
  - Notes on expenses and envelope, Undated (Box 1, File 2)
- Personal Ornithological Materials
  - “Beauty, Song and Habits Make Cardinal Tennessee’s Favorite Bird” by George R. Mayfield, Undated (Box 1, File 3)
  - “Mayfield Misses Song of Nightingale” by George R. Mayfield, Undated (Box 1, File 3)
  - “Publicity and Education as Factors in the Growth of Tennessee Ornithological Society” by George R. Mayfield, Undated (Box 1, File 3)
  - “Observation On the Flocking of Certain Birds in Autumn” 1940 review of “Trail of an Artist-Naturalist: the autobiography of Ernest Thompson Seton, Undated 1940 (Box 1, File 3)
  - “Large Bird Roost in West Nashville”, 1945-1946 (Box 1, File 3)
  - Film evaluation form, 1946-1947 (Box 1, File 3)
  - “Tennessee as Bird State”, Undated (Box 1, File 3)
  - “An Adventure with the American Condor” (Box 1, File 3)
  - “History of Roosts” (Box 1, File 3)
  - Mocking Bird poem (Box 1, File 3)
  - Poem “A Bird’s Concert” (Box 1, File 3)
  - Poem by Robert W. Service (Box 1, File 3)
  - “The Cat-Bird” by John Trotwood Moore (Box 1, File 3)
  - “Two Preachers” by John Trotwood Moore (Box 1, File 3)
  - loose book pages (Box 1, File 3)
  - “One Bluebird Does Not Make Spring” (Box 1, File 3)
  - untitled article on Starlings (Box 1, File 3)
  - untitled article on Nesting Materials (Box 1, File 3)
  - page 2 of unknown article (Box 1, File 3)
  - poem “the Ostrich” (Box 1, File 3)
  - article “Wishful Thinking” (Box 1, File 3)
  - page 4 Wildlife news (Box 1, File 3)
  - “The Winter Status of Certain Birds in Tennessee” (Box 1, File 3)
  - memos (Box 1, File 3)
- Ornithological Programs and Papers
  - American Ornithologists’ Union program, October 22-25, 1934, October 22-24, 1935 (Box 1, File 4)
  - National Association of Audubon Societies program, October 26-29, 1935 (Box 1, File 4)
  - The Wilson Ornithological Club program, November 20-23, 1941 (Box 1, File 4)
  - “Status of the Beaver and Otter in Tennessee” by Vincent Schultz from Journal of the Tennessee Academy of Science, January 1954 (Box 1, File 4)
  - Itinerary Georgia Ornithological Society, April 16, 1955 (Box 1, File 4)
  - Undated, Leaflet “The Egret” by T. Gilbert Pearson (Box 1, File 4)
  - Leaflet “Water Turkey” by T. Gilbert Pearson (Box 1, File 4)
  - Leaflet “The Bluebird” Roger T. Peterson (Box 1, File 4)
  - Leaflet Roosevelt Bird Sanctuary (Box 1, File 4)
  - Membership invitation to George R. Mayfield from (Box 1, File 4)
  - Audubon Societies (Box 1, File 4)
  - Print Group of Herons (Box 1, File 4)
  - Bird House measurements (Box 1, File 4)
  - Print of birds (Box 1, File 4)
  - Large folded print of birds (Box 1, File 4)
  - Large envelope with handwriting (Box 1, File 4)
- Vanderbilt Theatre Programs
  - Faust Program, April 7, 1932 (Box 1, File 5)
  - Auffuehrung Von Meisterschaft Program, March 7, 1933 (Box 1, File 5)
  - “Spring Has Come” by Vanderbilt Cap and Bells Club Program, May 4-6, 1933 (Box 1, File 5)
  - Alice in Wonderland by Vanderbilt Co-Eds Program, May 12, 1933 (Box 1, File 5)
  - Love of the Nations by Vanderbilt Co-Eds Program, May 8, 1934 (Box 1, File 5)
  - “Going Ga-Ga” by Vanderbilt Cap and Bells Club Program, May 10-12, 1934 (Box 1, File 5)
  - Deutsche Abteilung Program, April 17, 1935 (Box 1, File 5)
  - Les Precieuses Ridicules and Les Deux Sourds Program, March 4, 1937 (Box 1, File 5)
  - The Mikado Vanderbilt Theatre Program, April 26-29, 1950 (Box 1, File 5)
  - The Mikado Vanderbilt Masque Club Program, Undated (Box 1, File 5)
  - Die Ferne Prinzessin and Die Kleinen Verwandten Programs (Box 1, File 5)
- Vanderbilt Musical Programs
  - Annual Vesper Service Program, June 15, 1913 (Box 1, File 6)
  - Aeolian Organ Recital Programs, November 4, 1931 (Box 1, File 6)
  - Vanderbilt Glee Club Programs, April 12-13, 1933 (Box 1, File 6)
  - Vanderbilt Glee Club Program, May 1, 1934 (Box 1, File 6)
  - All-University Thanksgiving Program, November 27, 1935 (Box 1, File 6)
  - Vanderbilt University A Cappella Chorus Program, May 10, 1938 (Box 1, File 6)
  - Vanderbilt University A Cappella Choir Program, December 8, 1940 (Box 1, File 6)
  - Vanderbilt University A Cappella Choir Program, December 14, 1941 (Box 1, File 6)
  - May Music Festival Programs, May 2-5, 1950 (Box 1, File 6)
  - Vanderbilt Glee Club Program, Undated (Box 1, File 6)
  - Flyer Vanderbilt A Capella Chorus (Box 1, File 6)
- Other Vanderbilt Materials
  - Chancellor Kirkland 40th year Celebration Program, June 12, 1933 (Box 1, File 7)
  - Institute of International Relations Pamphlet, July 1-11, 1934 (Box 1, File 7)
  - Itinerary and application form (Box 1, File 7)
  - Nashville Institute of International Relations Pamphlet, June 25-July 5, 1935 (Box 1, File 7)
  - reprint “History of Medical Education at Vanderbilt University School of, January 1935 (Box 1, File 7)
  - Medicine” by James H. Kirkland from Journal of the Association of (Box 1, File 7)
  - American Medical Colleges (Box 1, File 7)
  - Institute of Public Affairs Programs, February 10-16, 1935 (Box 1, File 7)
  - The Vanderbilt Institute of Public Affairs Programs, April 7-10, 1936 (Box 1, File 7)
  - Dr. Wilbur Fisk Tillett Memorial Service Program, November 1, 1936 (Box 1, File 7)
  - The Cole Lectures Program, 1934, 1936, 1937 (Box 1, File 7)
  - Faculty Alumni Forum Program, October 23, 1941 (Box 1, File 7)
  - Joint University Library Dedication Exercises Program, December 5-6, 1941 (Box 1, File 7)
  - Pamphlet on Dean of Alumni Madison Sarratt, Undated (Box 1, File 7)
  - Living Endowment fund Alumni letter and envelope to Jerry C. Welsh (Box 1, File 7)
  - Invitation to tea with President and Mrs. Charles W. Eliot (Box 1, File 7)
  - Program itinerary (Box 1, File 7)
  - Admission booklet for Vanderbilt College of Arts and Science (Box 1, File 7)
- George Mayfield Vanderbilt Calendar
  - Personal Calendar, 1956 (Box 1, File 8)
- Language Association Materials
  - South Atlantic Modern Language Association Program, December 1-2, 1933 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Smoker Program, December 29, 1933 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Modern Language Association of America Programs, December 28-30, 1933 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Tennessee Philological Association Program, March 2-3, 1934 (Box 2, File 1)
  - South Atlantic Modern Language Association Members List, November 30, 1934 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Modern Language Association of America Programs, December 27-29, 1934 (Box 2, File 1)
  - South Atlantic Modern Language Association Program, November 29-30, 1935 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Modern Language Association of America Programs, December 30, 1935- January 1, 1936 (Box 2, File 1)
  - And Itinerary (Box 2, File 1)
  - Tennessee Philological Association Program, March 6-7, 1936 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Modern Language Association of America Program, December 29-31, 1936 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Tennessee Philological Association Program, March 5-6, 1937 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Classical Association of the Middle West and South Program, March 25-27, 1937 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Modern Language Association of America Program, December 28-30, 1937 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Subscription Dinner Program, December 29, 1937 (Box 2, File 1)
  - Banquet Songs Program (Box 2, File 1)
  - Tennessee Philological Association Programs, March 4-5, 1938 (Box 2, File 1)
- Tennessee Academy of Science Programs
  - November 27-28, 1931 (Box 2, File 2)
  - April 28-30, 1933 (Box 2, File 2)
  - November 30, December 1, 1934 (Box 2, File 2)
  - November 29-30, 1935 (Box 2, File 2)
  - November 27-28, 1936 (Box 2, File 2)
  - May 7-8, 1937 (Box 2, File 2)
  - May 6-7, 1938 (Box 2, File 2)
  - November 29-30, 1940 (Box 2, File 2)
- Other Organization Materials
  - Appalachian Trail Program, June 12-14, 1931 (Box 2, File 3)
  - George Peabody College for Teachers Program, February 18, 1935 (Box 2, File 3)
  - Garden Study Club of Nashville Program, 1940-1941 (Box 2, File 3)
  - Nashville Children’s Museum Program, October 30, 1945 (Box 2, File 3)
  - The Review Appeal Clipping, January 6, 1949 (Box 2, File 3)
  - New Horizons Bulletin, Spring 1955 (Box 2, File 3)
- Herbert Sanborn Materials
  - “The Dogma of Non-Transference” reprinted from Peabody Journal of Education by Herbert Sanborn, September 1927 (Box 2, File 4)
  - “Dingler’s Methodical Philosophy” by Herbert Sanborn, 1952 (Box 2, File 4)
  - “Thucydides on History as Philosophy” by Herbert Sanborn, April 1955 (Box 2, File 4)
  - “The Southern Philosopher” Vol. IV, no. 3 writings by Sanborn, July 1955 (Box 2, File 4)
  - Herbert Sanborn’s Senatorial Platform, Undated (Box 2, File 4)
- Chancellor Heard Materials
  - Program 25th Anniversary of Vanderbilt and Kissam Hall Opening, October 21-23, 1900 (Box 2, File 5)
  - State of the University report program, September 1, 1947 (Box 2, File 5)
  - Vanderbilt Founder’s Day program, May 3, 1950 (Box 2, File 5)
  - State of the University report program, September 26, 1952 (Box 2, File 5)
  - Program for the Installation of George (Alexander) Heard as Chancellor, October 4, 1963 (Box 2, File 5)
- Music Programs and Clippings
  - Student Prince in Heidelberg program, December 21-26, 1927 (Box 2, File 6)
  - Nashville Symphony Orchestra Program, Season 1945-1950 (Box 2, File 6)
  - Hillsboro Presbyterian Church Program, January 8, 1950 (Box 2, File 6)
  - Athenians of Vanderbilt University Program, April 13, 1950 (Box 2, File 6)
  - Cathedral Singers Program, March 23, 1958 (Box 2, File 6)
  - Newspaper clippings Dance in-the-round concert, Undated (Box 2, File 6)
  - Old Harp Singers of Nashville, Tennessee programs (Box 2, File 6)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Newspaper clipping Vanderbilt Hustler, November 11, 1949 (Box 2, File 7)
  - Newspaper clippings Nashville Banner, May 5, 1961 (Box 2, File 7)
  - Newspaper clippings Nashville Banner, June 3, 1961 (Box 2, File 7)
  - Newspaper clipping Nashville Banner, June 10, 1966 (Box 2, File 7)
  - Newspaper clipping Nashville Banner, June 11, 1966 (Box 2, File 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 2, File 7)
- Newspaper Clippings that were photocopied in File 7
  - (Box 2, File 8)